A Guide to the F. Champion Ward Professional Papers FA1450
Rockefeller Archive Center
F. Champion Ward professional papers
1940-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ward, F. Champion (1910-2007)
Ford Foundation
FA1450
3.42 Cubic Feet 8 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter document boxes
Scope and Contents
General Papers of F. Champion Ward
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was donated and transferred to the RAC in 2016 by the Geoffrey C. Ward and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2016:043.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Letters to/from VIPs, 1949-2007
Series 2. Collected Papers, 1945-2007
Biographical / Historical
Frederick Champion Ward was born on December 29, 1910 in New Brunswick, New Jersey. He graduated from Oberlin College in 1932 and was awarded a master's in philosophy in 1935. He went on to earn a doctorate in philosophy from Yale in 1937. He taught philosophy and psychology from 1937 to 1945 at Denison University and, as Associate Dean, trained military officers for de-Nazification efforts in postwar Germany. After the war, Dr. Ward joined the faculty of the University of Chicago and served as Dean of the undergraduate Humanities Division from 1947 to 1954.
In 1954, Dr. Ward took leave from the university to travel to India for the Ford Foundation. Upon his return, he joined the Foundation as Director of the Overseas Development Program for the Middle East and Africa. He later became Deputy Vice President for International Programs. In 1965, he was promoted to Vice President of Education and Research, a position he held until 1967 when he became a Program Advisor to International Division's Office of the Vice President. He retired from the Foundation in 1977.
During the 1960s Dr. Ward served as Chairman of the White House Task Force on the Education of Gifted Persons and was a member of the UNESCO International Commission on the Development of Education.
After his retirement from the Foundation, Dr. Ward worked as a consultant for the World Bank, the Association of American Universities, and the Connecticut Board of Education. From 1978 to 1981, he was a senior consultant to the Board of the MacArthur Foundation and helped establish the "genius grant." Dr. Ward also served as Chancellor of the New School for Social Research in Manhattan from 1980 to 1983. He died on July 2, 2007 at the age of 96.
- Letters to/from VIPs, 1949-2007; 1; 1.52 Cubic Feet 4 letter document boxes
  - Max Frankel, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chester Bowles, 1954-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Austill, 1993-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ART, 2006 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Abbott, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Elleson, Gregory II, 1976-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bunselmeyer, 2003 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Johnette Cole, 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Robert Collins, 2003 January 5-30 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conninqqim, 1995 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cramer, 1954-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - John Boyer, 1988-2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bresnan, 1965-2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Berresford, 2005 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jacques Barzon, 1975-2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Bill Benten, 1964 March 6-August 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rosenheim, 1954-1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sommers, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Humanistic View, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bundy, 1996-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Doc Howe, 1971-2000 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Frosty Hill, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Heaps, 1987-2005 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Faust, 1973 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bill McNeill, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Lew Morrill, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Reuben Frodin, 1993-2006 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Fuller, 1973-2006 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 60th Reunion, 1993-1998 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Rorty, 1982-2003 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Riesman, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Galbraith, 1981-1994 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Levi, 1964-2001 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Hutchins (Personal), 1949-1995 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Coleman, 1983-2005 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Denison Studen, 1974-1992 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Wilma Ebbitt, 1989-1999 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Edwards, Bob, 1988-2005 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Levine, 1984-2003 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Dick, 1959 September 17 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Magat, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Malhotra, 1969-2005 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Nolte, 1998-2004 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Northrop, 1954-2001 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - David ORR, 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Ravitch, 2001-2006 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Ebbitt, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - SAMS, 1973-1981 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Streeter, 1962-2004 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Charles Wegener, 1954-2004 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Wilsons, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Francis Sutton (6 folders), 1962-2007 (Box 3, Folder 52-57, Box 4, Folder 58)
- Collected Papers, 1940-2007; 2; 2.28 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter document boxes
  - A Life In Two Worlds: Recollections and Reflections, 1995 August (Box 4, Folder 59)
  - Drafted Memoirs, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Challenges to the American College Thoughts and Second Thoughts, undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
  - Heraclitus, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - Challenges to the American College Thoughts and Second Thoughts (draft), undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Drafts of Foreword, undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
  - Remembering Champ, 2007 August 12 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - A Connecticut Yankee in the Third World, undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
  - Chapter Two, 1964-2001 (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - For Dewy, undated (Box 4, Folder 69)
  - New Ms., undated (Box 4, Folder 70)
  - Book Two, undated (Box 4, Folder 71)
  - Glimpses of the High and Mighty, 2003 February (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - ACTA, 2003-2006 (Box 4, Folder 73)
  - The Age of Innocence - Essays, 1975 June (Box 4, Folder 74)
  - To India, 1994 March (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - A Life In Two Worlds: Recollections and Reflections, 1995 August (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Aspen College, 1952-1975 (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - Ignorance, Arrogance, and Good Will, 2007 January 27 (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Centennial Dinner, University of Chicago, 1984-1995 (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Commentary on Windham, 1975 June (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Cross-Pollination in Higher Education, 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Empire Relinquished, undated (Box 5, Folder 82)
  - England, 1950-1951 (Box 5, Folder 83)
    Scope and Contents
    academic testing paraphernalia; newsletters; correspondences
  - Casuals, 1993-2003 (Box 5, Folder 84)
  - The Birth and Infancy of the MacArthur Fellows Program, 1981-2003 (Box 5, Folder 85)
  - Letter re Middle East, 2001-2004 (Box 5, Folder 86)
  - Pet Schemer, undated (Box 5, Folder 87)
  - Polarities in Indian Educational Thought, 1957 December (Box 5, Folder 88)
    Includes articles: 'Some Polarities In Indian Educational Thought', and 'Principles and Particulars in Liberal Education
  - Principle and Particulars in Liberal Education, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Catalogs and College Brochures, 1953-1999 (Box 6, Folder 90)
  - Redirection in Educational Development, 1975 May (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Reflections, 2001-2003 (Box 6, Folder 92)
  - Requiem for the Hutchins College, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Retired Pioneer, 1973 October 23 (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Returning Coal to Newcastle, undated (Box 6, Folder 95)
    Original folder empty of content. Content appears to be in the following "Returning Coals" file.
  - Returning Coals, 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 96)
    Items named "Returning Coals to Newcastle" are most likely misplaced from previous file.
  - Book Reviews, 1951-1987 (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Social Progress and the Liberal Arts, 1970 June 1 (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Tchq and Res, 1985-2002 (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Toward a Congenial Progress, 1985-1986 (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - What Did Confucius Say?, 1958-1961 (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - The University of Chicago B.A. College, 1949-1962 (Box 6, Folder 102)
  - Fabric of Universities, 1969 March 2 (Box 6, Folder 103)
  - From Manpower to Mankind, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 104)
  - Grad Ed, 2005 October 21 (Box 6, Folder 105)
  - Graduate Schools, 1974-2006 (Box 6, Folder 106)
  - Idea of World University, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 107)
  - Sins of Commissions, undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
  - Knowing, Doing and Making, undated (Box 6, Folder 109)
  - Language, 1985-2005 (Box 7, Folder 110)
  - Learning to Be, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Liberal and Legal Education, 1952 December 4 (Box 7, Folder 112)
  - What Did Confucius Say? (Reprint from the Journal of General Education, January 1958), 1992-2004 (Box 7, Folder 113)
  - The University of Chicago Announcements The College for Sessions of 1952-1953, 1952 May 10 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - The University of Chicago Student Essay Annual Vol. 1 No. 2, 1952 October (Box 7, Folder 115)
  - Uncorrected Page Proof Hutchins' University: A Memoir of the University of Chicago, 1929-1950, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 116)
  - A Life in Two Worlds: Recollections and Reflections, 1995 August (Box 7, Folder 117)
  - The College Faculty 1953-1954, 1953 October 1 (Box 7, Folder 118)
  - Writing and Talks II Education and Development (2 folders), 1956-2002 (Box 7, Folder 119-120)
    Education and Development; India; Indian Colleagues; Modes of Planning; Learning To Be; U.S. Policy Abroad
  - Assorted Correspondences, 1985-2004 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    Includes additional personal and professional correspondences.
  - Situation Vacant, 1945-1964 (Box 8, Folder 122)
    Letters from Educational Institutions offering F. C. W. various academic positions - all of which he gently turned down.
  - Miscellaneous Letters and Documents (2 folders), 1940-2003 (Box 8, Folder 123, Box 9, Folder 124)
    Includes the following labels: Letters on Foreign Policy; Letters To The Editor; Philanthropy; The Ford Foundation (Policies and Habits); Casuals; Language; Miscellaneous Letters 1; Miscellaneous Letters 2; Pet Schemet and Notions; Denison
  - Chapter Six: The Ruinous Cost of College, 2006 September 15 (Box 9, Folder 125)
  - Hutchins College Revisited, 2005 November 18 (Box 9, Folder 126)
  - Appointments and Departures (3 folders), 1953-2002 (Box 9, Folder 127-129)
    Denison; Family Letters; College Faculty; Indian Colleagues; Other Indians; V.P. Ford Foundation; Trustees; Immediate Colleagues; "International" Colleagues; Others; New School Administrators; New school Faculty; Whiting Foundation Departure
  - Ford Foundation in India (2 folders), 1949-2001 (Box 9, Folder 130, Box 10, Folder 131)
    Cos Cob School Closing
  - Fellows Interviewed, 1982-1984 (Box 10, Folder 132)